JANELLA YAR VALENZUELA

Atlanta Metro | (770) 374-7449 janevalen00@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/jyvalenzuela

Aspiring IT PROFESSIONAL (CHEMICAL ENGINEER)

Result-oriented chemical engineer with 5+ years of working experience in research and development within materials, solutions, and chemical industry. Seeking an entry-level position where I can grow and learn from experienced members in computer programming. I am adaptive person in new work environment and offer a strong analytical background and entry-level coding skills in MATLAB and Python. Recently accepted into Georgia Tech Coding Bootcamp, will assisting part-time.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Software: MATLAB +Simulink, Python (beginner), Aspen Plus, ChemDraw, AutoCAD (2D), Autodesk Inventor (3D), Microsoft Office Suite, Google Drive, Labware, Lotus notes, DoE, Tecan, HPLC, Minitab

AREAS of EFFECTIVENESS

Problem Solving, Critical Thinking, Bilingual (Spanish/English), Data interpretation and analysis, Technical writing, Process Optimization, Customer Service, Leadership, Teamwork, Troubleshooting, Time Management

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Solvay Specialty Polymers - Alpharetta, GA

02/2020 - 01/2023

Production Engineer II

- Optimized existing formulation and processes to improve product performance, process robustness and safety while reducing costs.
- Plan and design research projects; specify the problem and define the project scope using Sig Sigma methodologies.
- Worked with management to evaluate future projects and align with critical path schedule requirements.
- Generated engineering and technical documentation to facilitate product development collaboration.

Production Engineer I

- Develop and implement prototypes and programs to explore and evaluate concepts, which can serve as proof-ofconcepts and demonstrations and can be used to run evaluations and collect data.
- Collaborate daily with a principal scientist to provide technical support for manufacturing sites, improve current manufacturing processes, and develop novel manufacturing processes.
- Analyze Engineering results and proposes product changes to determine feasibility, improvement of component and systems, and functional and performance specifications.

American Heritage Biomass LLC- Georgia Tech Renewable Bioproducts Institute Research Specialist

08/2011 - 01/2020

- Combine and leverage my knowledge of chemical engineering and polymer science to aid the design and execution of experiments that gather comprehensive data on the synthesis and processing of polymers.
- Designed an experimental procedure to determine the chemical and physical properties of the pineapple biomass known as bromelain.
- Identified cost-effective recipes containing 100% of natural, bio-based, and biodegradable ingredients yielding potential savings of 63%.
- Apply statistical methodologies to process collected experimental and analytical data and inform the next steps in the design process

Import Trading LLC- Georgia Tech Renewable Bioproducts Institute

08/2018 - 05/2019

Research Technician

Proposed a future bio-based, biodegradable, compostable and recyclable spoon to be able to diminish pollution, decrease animal death in oceans and other environments and biodegrade 200 times faster than current plastic spoons.

- Established a protocol to evaluate and select sustainable alternatives for the replacement of synthetic and non-biodegradable silverware.
- Performed experiments that involved injection molding and stress tests to find alternatives for flatware.
- Identified sources of funding to prepare research proposals and submit funding applications.
- Advised or assisted in obtaining patents or meeting other legal requirements.

EDUCATION & ACHIEVEMENTS

Georgia Institute of Technology - Bachelor of Science in Chemical Engineering | 2019

- Dean's List 2015-2019
- Graduated with Honors
- 2019 Capstone Winner for Chitin Nanofiber production; a bioplastic alternative, sponsored by Niagara Water

Lean Six Sigma Certifications

- White Belt
- Yellow Belt
- Green Belt (in progress)

Pulp and Paper Certification | Georgia Institute of Technology July 2019

adds in education and remove from intro SS, completed professional teaching in Devops, Git (IMPORTANT) for interview. More professiom. Accepted gt bootcamp will be doinh PT, title (aspiring IT professional), CHEME, add link of ceritifcate from coursea in education section apply before 28 Oct, application closes

get subscriptoion from coursea